<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="exercise.xsd"?>
<exercise title="09.08 Lottery" difficulty="hard" size="L" returnbox="http://hhmoodle.haaga-helia.fi/mod/assign/view.php?id=402567&amp;action=editsubmission" template="xc/09.08.html">

<p class="exercise_text"> 
After the successful cottage retreat people decided to make a draw (raffle/lottery, arpajaiset) for deciding who gets the remaining food. Make a program that asks for the name of all the attendants and randomize the winner.
<p class="exercise_gui_title">Sample output after two names have been added:</p>
<p><img src="xc/09.08.png" class="bordered"/>
</p>

<p class="exercise_gui_title">Sample output after several names have been added AND the draw has been made:
<img src="xc/09.08b.png" class="bordered"/>
</p>
<p>
HINTS:
</p>
<ol type="a">
<li>Asks for the name of all the attendants
<ul>
<li>Define the array variable and create the array object inside the script element, but NOT inside the function. Then it will be global and thus available for all functions to read from or write to.
<pre><code>var names = [];  // defining a variable and creating empty array object </code></pre></li>
<li>When the Add button is pressed assign the name from the input field to the array 
<pre><code>names[index] = document.getElementById("name").value;
index = index + 1; </code></pre> </li>
<li>Empty the input field as that name was just put in the array
<pre><code>document.getElementById("name").value = ""; </code></pre> </li>
<li>Additionally show the inserted names so far under the input field:
<ul>
<li>Go through the array in a for loop adding each name at the end of the namesText. </li>
<li>Set that text to HTML document</li>
</ul>
 </li>
</ul>
</li>

<li>Randomize the winner
<ul>
<li>When "Make the draw" button is pressedRandomize the index of the winner: 
<pre><code>var winningIndex = Math.floor(Math.random() * names.length);</code></pre>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
</p> 

<p>Submit a link to your code (myy or jsbin). </p>
	<a class="jsbin-embed" href="http://jsbin.com/baguje/embed?html,js,output">JS Bin</a>
</exercise>