<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="exercise.xsd"?>
<exercise id="13.03" title="Identity Number" difficulty="medium" size="M" 
returnbox="http://hhmoodle.haaga-helia.fi/mod/assign/view.php?id=397061&amp;action=editsubmission" 
template="xc/13.03.html">

<p class="exercise_text"> 
Make a program, that asks for the identity number (Finnish 'hetu', 11 characters) and tells, whether the person is male or female. The second last character of the identity number tells the gender: even digit/number means woman, odd number man.
Program also tells the date of birth in the format of dd.mm.yyyy.
</p>
<p class="exercise_gui_title">Sample output for shown input:</p>
<p><img src="xc/13.03.png" class="bordered"/> </p>
<p>HINTS:</p>
<p>
<ul>
<li>Telling, whether the person is male or female. The second last character of the identity number tells the gender: even digit/number means woman, odd number man.
<ul> 
<li>The charAt() method can be used to get the second last character.</li> 
<li>The parseInt() function can be used to convert number text to number.</li>
<li>If you take a remainder of that number divided by 2 with the remainder/modulo operator % you will get to know if the number is odd or even. (E.g. 7 % 2 gives 1 for the remainder, thus 7 is an odd number).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Telling the date of birth in the format of dd.mm.yyyy. If the identity number has '+' as the separator character then the century is 1800. If the separator is '-', the century is 1900. If the separator is 'A', the century is 2000. 
<ul>
<li>With the subStr() method you can take certain characters from the original string. </li>
<li>The charAt() method gives you the separator.</li>
<li>The parseInt() function can be used to convert number text to number.</li>
<li>You need to do some calculation with numbers to attach the century to the year.</li>
</ul>
</li> 
</ul>
</p> 
<p class="exercise_gui_title">Sample output for shown input:</p>
<p>
<img src="xc/13.03b.png" class="bordered"/>
<img src="xc/13.03c.png" class="bordered"/>
</p>
<p>Submit a link to your code (myy or jsbin). </p>


</exercise>