<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/course.xsl"?>
<course logo="img/app.svg" title="Orientation to Software Engineering">


	<part title="COURSE INFO" icon="off" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		<p>Welcome to the course Orientation to Software Engineering (SWD1TN001).
		Please attend the first lecture to learn more about the course. Still the most important information about the course is written on this site.</p>
		<slides title="Welcome to the course" url="slides/part0.html"/>
		<p>Check out the schedule of this course including lectures and lab sessions.
		Click the assessment button if you want to see how to pass this course and how many points you can get from an exercise.
		You should check out the learning objectives to understand where to focus during studies.</p>
		<subpage icon="time" title="Schedule">
		<h4>Weekly Objectives</h4>
			<table class="table table-striped table-bordered table-condensed">
				<tr><th>WEEK</th><th>CONTENT</th></tr>
				<tr><td>1</td><td>COURSE INFO, PART 1, PART 2</td></tr>
				<tr><td>2</td><td>PART 3, PART 4</td></tr>
				<tr><td>3</td><td>PART 5, PART 6</td></tr>
				<tr><td>4</td><td>PART 7, PART 8</td></tr>
				<tr><td>5</td><td>PART 9, PART 10</td></tr>
				<tr><td>6</td><td>PART 11, PART 12</td></tr>
				<tr><td>7</td><td>ROUNDUP, EXAM</td></tr>
				<tr><td>8</td><td>LESSONS LEARNED</td></tr>
			</table>
			<h4>Keynote Lectures</h4>
			<p><b>IN ENGLISH:</b><br/>On Wednesdays and Fridays at 09:00-09:45, Place: Pasila 2209</p><br/>
			<p><b>IN FINNISH:</b><br/>On Wednesdays at 09:00-10:30 (except 4.11.)</p>
			<table class="table table-striped table-bordered table-condensed">
				<tr><th>Week</th><th>Place</th><th>Date</th></tr>
				<tr><td>1</td><td>1201 (Auditorium)</td><td>Wed 28.10.2015 at klo 09:00 - 10:30</td></tr>
				<tr><td>2</td><td>NO KEYNOTES</td><td>NO KEYNOTES</td></tr>
				<tr><td>3</td><td>1001</td><td>Wed 11.11.2015 at 09:00 - 10:30</td></tr>
				<tr><td>4</td><td>6205</td><td>Wed 18.11.2015 at 09:00 - 10:30</td></tr>
				<tr><td>5</td><td>1201</td><td>Wed 25.11.2015 at 09:00 - 10:30</td></tr>
				<tr><td>6</td><td>6205</td><td>Wed 02.12.2015 at 09:00 - 10:30</td></tr>
				<tr><td>7</td><td>1201</td><td>Wed 09.12.2015 at 09:00 - 10:30</td></tr>
				<tr><td>8</td><td>1201</td><td>Wed 16.12.2015 at 09:00 - 10:30</td></tr>
			</table>
			<h3>Lab Sessions</h3>
			<table class="table table-striped table-bordered table-condensed">
				<tr><th>Study unit code</th><th>Language</th><th>Time and Place</th></tr>
				<tr><td>SWD1TN001-1</td><td>In Finnish</td><td>Web 09:00-12:00 (4207),<br/>Fri 09:00-12:00 (4207)</td></tr>
				<tr><td>SWD1TN001-2</td><td>In Finnish</td><td>Web 09:00-12:00 (5015),<br/>Fri 09:00-12:00 (5015)</td></tr>
				<tr><td>SWD1TN001-3</td><td>In Finnish</td><td>Wed 09:00-12:00 (5009),<br/>Fri 12:00-15:00 (5007)</td></tr>
				<tr><td>SWD1TN001-4</td><td>In Finnish</td><td>Tue 13:00-16:00 (4012),<br/>Wed 09:00-12:00 (5008)</td></tr>
				<tr><td>SWD1TN001-5</td><td>In Finnish</td><td>Tue 09:00-12:00 (5015),<br/>Thu 12:00-15:00 (5015)</td></tr>
				<tr><td>SWD1TF001-1</td><td>In English</td><td>Web 10:00-11:45 (4009),<br/>Fri 10:00-11:45 (4009)</td></tr>
				<tr><td>SWD1TF001-2</td><td>In English</td><td>Web 10:00-11:45 (4012),<br/>Fri 10:00-11:45 (4012)</td></tr>
				<tr><td>SWD1TA001-1</td><td>In Finnish<br/>(blended learning)</td><td>Mon 17:40-20:30 (5007 and 5009),<br/>Thu 17:40-20:30 (5015 and 5009)</td></tr>
			</table>
		</subpage>
		<subpage icon="adjust" title="Assessment">
			<h4>Rules</h4>
			<p><b>PASS</b><br/> YOU HAVE TO (earn at least 25% of the maximum exercise points) AND (get at least 50 points from the exam) TO PASS THE COURSE.</p><br/>
				<p><b>GRADE</b><br/> THE EXAM POINTS DEFINE YOUR BASE GRADE.</p><br/>
				<p><b>BONUS</b><br/> IF YOU HAVE (earned at least 75% of the maximum exercise points) AND (passed the exam), YOUR GRADE WILL BE UPGRADED BY 1.<br/>
				(designated course implementations will give bonus also from social activities.)</p><br/>
			<h4>Exercise points</h4>
			<p>The exercises are categorized by sizes (S-XL) and difficulties (1-3 stars).
			You should return only ready/working solutions to the exercise return boxes.
			It is illegal to return uncompleted exercises.
			If you are stuck with an exercise, ask for help in a lab session to complete your solution.
			Spot checks are carried out by teachers and uncompleted solutions will cause sanctions.</p>
			<table class="table table-striped table-bordered table-condensed">
			<tr><th>Size</th><th>Points</th></tr>
			<tr><td>S</td><td>1p</td></tr>
			<tr><td>M</td><td>2p</td></tr>
			<tr><td>L</td><td>3p</td></tr>
			<tr><td>XL</td><td>5p</td></tr>
			</table>
			
			<h5>Exam points</h5>
			<table class="table table-striped table-bordered table-condensed">
			<tr><th>Points</th><th>Grade</th></tr>
			<tr><td>&gt;90p</td><td>5</td></tr>
			<tr><td>80-89p</td><td>4</td></tr>
			<tr><td>70-79p</td><td>3</td></tr>
			<tr><td>60-69p</td><td>2</td></tr>
			<tr><td>50-59p</td><td>1</td></tr>
			<tr><td>&lt;50p</td><td>0</td></tr>
			</table>
			
		</subpage>		
		<subpage icon="th-list" title="Learning objectives">
			Student is able to explain the software engineering profile and the rough contents of its courses. She/he is able to communicate the components and phases of software engineering (software development). She is able to implement web pages that contain simple functionality implemented with browser programming. She is able to use the needed development tools and publish the pages on a web server. She is able to utilize technical documentation while needing information or help.
			The course gives a broad view on Software Engineering and software development, and the brief basics of programming:
			<ul>
				<li>software engineering; goals, main concepts, and challenges</li>
				<li>main phases/disciplines in software engineering processes</li>
				<li>few methods and models visualizing the software development work in practice</li>
				<li>main principles for creating technically sound web pages (with HTML5 and CSS)</li>
				<li>development environment and publishing the web site on a web server</li>
				<li>all linkages between the web page and the JavaScript program</li>
				<li>designing and implementing simple programming logic</li>
				<li>using following features of the programming language: selection and repetition structures, arrays and functions</li>
				<li>the technical documentation needed in basic web development and the ways to utilize it</li>
			</ul>
		</subpage>
		<p>Please give feedback immediately after noticing issues before you forget them. You can give feedback about course contents, pedagogics, lectures, text material, videos, lab sessions, exercise assignments, development tools, web site bugs or whatever you think the teachers should be noticed of.</p>
		<subpage icon="envelope" title="Feedback">
			<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1rdmDV-AsfMniQiKceC3seCKloT7-yuOUDeI2EBtEYRs/viewform?embedded=true" width="450" height="1000" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading...</iframe>
		</subpage>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
			<badgeImg><img src="img/badge00.png" alt="Badge 0" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
			<ol>
				<li>Why this course is important?</li>
				<li>What can I do after this course?</li>
				<li>How to pass this course?</li>
				<li>How to study to get the best learning experience?</li>
				<li>Where can I find the theory?</li>
				<li>How to solve the exercises?</li>
				<li>When is the Exam?</li>
				<li>What kind of questions there is in the exam?</li>
				<li>How to prepare to the exam?</li>
				<li>What are the contents of this course?</li>
				<li>What the assessment criteria?</li>
			</ol>
		</section>
	</part>

	<part title="1 Software Development" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		<p>Let's take a look at the industry, discuss the basic concepts and view what kind of education our curriculum provides.</p> 
		<slides title="Slideshow" url="slides/part1.html"/>
		<p>Learning to make applications by yourself is a vital skill to understand the challenges that there is in software development.</p>
            <p><br/>"<b>Software development</b> is the process by which a company, team, or individual devises and implements an overall plan to create a new software program. Writing code is just one step of the software development process. The process usually begins with research or a general understanding of what type of software is needed in the marketplace. Once those involved in software development have a goal for the program they are working on, they can begin developing the plan for implementing the software." (<a href="http://www.wisegeek.com/what-is-software-development.htm">Wisegeek</a>)</p>            
		<p><br/>"An <b>Application</b> is a program, or group of programs, that is designed for the end user. Software can be divided into  two general classes: systems software and applications software. Applications software (also called end-user programs) include such things as word processors, Web browsers, spreadsheets and databases." (<a href="http://www.webopedia.com/TERM/A/application.html">Webopedia</a>)</p>
            <p><br/>"A <b>programming language</b> is a special language programmers use to develop applications, scripts, or other set of instructions for computers to execute. Choosing a programming language takes a lot of consideration: what do you want to do with the language, what platforms you're working with, applicability to the problem domain and more." (<a href="http://www.computerhope.com/jargon/p/proglang.htm">Computer Hope</a>)</p>
                        <bookmark title="Wikipedia: List of programming languages" url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_programming_languages"/>
            <p><br/><b>Programming</b></p>
            <video title="What is programming" youtubeid="3tWMQ3ZMjbg"/>
            <p><br/><b>Interpreters</b> and <b>Compilers</b></p>
            <bookmark title="What are they?" url="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_C5AHaS1mOA"/>
        </section>
        		
        
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
			<exercise file="xc/01.02.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/01.03.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
			<badgeImg><img src="img/badge01.png" alt="Badge 1" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
			<ol>
				<li>Why software development is interesting?</li>
				<li>What is a program?</li>
				<li>What kind of programs there are?</li>
				<li>What is an application?</li>
				<li>What is programming?</li>
				<li>What kind of programming languages there are?</li>
				<li>What is a compiler?</li>
				<li>What is an interpreter?</li>
				<li>How applications are developed?</li>
				<li>What kind of markets there are for software development?</li>
				<li>What kind of markets there are for software developers?</li>
				<li>What kind of courses does the curriculum provide?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>


	<part title="2 Algorithms" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		<slides title="Slideshow" url="slides/part2.html"/>
		<bookmark title="Blockly Maze Game" url="https://blockly-games.appspot.com/maze?lang=en"/>
		<p>"An algorithm is any well-defined computational procedure that takes some value, or set of values, as input and produces some value, or set of values as output." In other words, algorithms are like road maps for accomplishing a given, well-defined task. (<i>Introduction to algorithms by Thomas H. Cormen, Charles E. Leiserson, Ronald L. Rivest, Clifford Stein</i>)</p>
        <p><img src="img/algorithm1.png"/></p>    
            <p><br/>One example of the algorithms is a code that calculates the terms of the Fibonacci sequence. Even a simple function for adding two numbers is an algorithm in a sense.</p>
            <p><br/>Algorithms can be expressed in many ways. One example is <b>Pseudocode</b>. Pseudocode contains following logical structures.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Sequence logic</li>
				<li>Selection logic</li>
				<li>Iteration logic</li> 
            </ul>
            <p>These structures are proven to be sufficient for writing any computer program.</p>
            <p><pre><code>Pseudocode example
IF HoursWorked > NormalMax
  Display overtime message
ELSE 
  Display regular time message
</code></pre></p>  
        <p><br/>The other example is <b>Flowchart</b> which graphically shows the logical steps to carry out a task.</p>
        <p><img width="400" src="img/flowchart.png"/></p>               
        <p>Both of these techniques are widely used today. There are lot of benefits to achive by using these techiques like:
  			<ul>
				<li>Effective analysis and design</li>
				<li>Proper documentation</li>
				<li>Efficient Coding</li> 
            </ul>      
        <br/> <a href="www2.sunysuffolk.edu/wakefid/CST141/Flowcharts.ppt">(Flowcharts and pseudocode, Debra Wakefield)</a></p>
<bookmark title="What's an algorithm?" url="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6hfOvs8pY1k"/>            
        </section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
			<exercise file="xc/02.01.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/02.02.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/02.03.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge02.png" alt="Badge 2" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>Where do I need algorithms?</li>
		<li>How to instruct the computer?</li>
		<li>What is the idea of a condition?</li>
		<li>What is the idea of a loop?</li>
		<li>When do we need variables?</li>
		<li>What is a flow chart?</li>
		<li>How to make my first algorithm with blockly?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	
	<part title="3 Environments" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		In what kind of an environment does the software run?
		What kind of an environment does a software developer need?
		This part will answer to these and some other important questions.
		<slides title="Slideshow" url="slides/part3.html"/>
		<video title="Haaga-Helia Xubuntu desktop" youtubeid="JDw1ii7aKwg"/>
		<video title="Write and publish a simple web page" youtubeid="JDw1ii7aKwg"/>
		<p>To see how to install Chromium browser on Xubuntu and how to use the developer toolbar, see the instructions below</p> 
		<subpage icon="wrench" title="Install Chromium Browser">
				<p><strong>Open Terminal Window</strong> by pressing</p>
				<pre><code class="language-none">Ctrl+Alt+T</code></pre>
				<p><strong>Install Chromium Browser</strong> by typing the following text into the terminal window</p>
				<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo apt-get install chromium-browser</code></pre>
				<p><strong>Open Chromium Browser</strong> by typing the following text into the terminal window</p>
				<pre><code class="language-bash">chromium-browser &amp;</code></pre>
				<p><strong>Open Developer Toolbar</strong> by pressing </p>
				<pre><code class="language-none">Ctrl+Shift+I</code></pre>
				<p>You can write a <strong>log</strong> text from your web page to the browser console by writing the following JavaScript-code. The console is located at the developer toolbar.</p>
				<pre><code class="language-javascript">Console.log("The text to be logged.");</code></pre>
		</subpage>
		
		<subpage icon="transfer" title="Access the production environment">
			<p>You can access the production environment with <strong>Secure Shell (SSH)</strong> by writing the following command in the terminal window</p>
			<pre><code class="language-bash">ssh username@servername
#for example
ssh a1234567@myy.haaga-helia.fi</code></pre>
			<p>On the remote host you can run common shell commands.</p>
			<p>Transferring a file from your local machine to the remote machine is easily done with <strong>Secure Copy (SCP)</strong> with the following command</p>
			<pre><code class="language-bash">scp filename username@servername:destinationfolder
#for example
scp mypage.html a1234567@myy.haaga-helia.fi:public_html
#or a folder and all of its subfolders recursively
scp -r foldername username@servername:destinationfolder</code></pre>
		</subpage>
		</section>
		
		
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
		<exercise file="xc/03.01.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/03.02.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/03.03.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/03.04.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/03.05.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/03.06.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/03.07.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/03.08.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge03.png" alt="Badge 3" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
			<li>What kind of environments does a software developer need?</li>
			<li>What kind of tools does a software developer need?</li>
			<li>How to use the editor?</li>
			<li>What does the server do?</li>
			<li>How to use a browser developer toolbar?</li>
			<li>How to print logs to the console?</li>
			<li>How to publish my first application on localhost?</li>
			<li>How to publish my first application on the Internet?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	
		<part title="4 JavaScript" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
			<slides title="Slideshow" url="slides/part4.html"/>
			<p style="color:red">TODO: CODE BLOCKS (head js, ext js, body js, onclick inline js)</p>
			<pre class="language-markup"><code>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
function myListener() {
	console.log(&quot;******************&quot;);
	console.log(&quot;* BUTTON PRESSED *&quot;);
	console.log(&quot;******************&quot;);
}
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
	&lt;button onclick=&quot;myListener()&quot;&gt;Press me!&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</code></pre>
<p>JavaScript is an object oriented dynamic language. Its syntax comes from Java and C languages. With JavaScript you can for example:
    <ul>
        <li>Change HTML content</li>
        <li>Change HTML attributes</li>
        <li>Change HTML styles</li>
        <li>Validate data</li>
    </ul></p>
    <p><br/>In HTML, JavaScript code must be inserted between &lt;script&gt; and &lt;/script&gt; tags.</p>
    <p>Example<pre><code>&lt;script&gt;
  document.getElementById("demo").innerHTML = "My First JavaScript";
&lt;/script&gt;</code></pre></p>
    <p>You can place any number of scripts in an HTML document.</p><p>Scripts can be placed in the &lt;body&gt;, or in the &lt;head&gt; section of an HTML page, or in both.</p>
    <p>Scripts can also be placed in external files. External scripts are practical when the same code is used in many different web pages. JavaScript files have the file extension<b>.js</b>.
</p><p><br/>JavaScript <b>comments</b> can be used to explain JavaScript code, and to make it more readable. Single line comments start with //. Any text between // and the end of the line, will be ignored by JavaScript.
</p>
            
            <p>Example<pre><code>//This is my First comment
&lt;script&gt;
  document.getElementById("demo").innerHTML = "My First JavaScript";
&lt;/script&gt;</code></pre></p><p>Multi-line comments start with /* and end with */. Any text between /* and */ will be ignored by JavaScript.
</p>
    <p><br/>The HTML <b>DOM</b> is a standard object model and programming interface for HTML. It defines:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>The HTML elements as objects</li>
        <li>The properties of all HTML elements </li>
        <li>The methods to access all HTML elements</li>
        <li>The events for all HTML elements</li>
    </ul>
    <p><br/>In other words: The HTML DOM is a standard for how to get, change, add, or delete HTML elements.</p>
    <p>The HTML DOM model is constructed as a tree of Objects</p>
    <p><img src="img/dom_tree.png"/></p>              
    <p><br/>Most JavaScript programs contain many JavaScript statements. Semicolons separate JavaScript statements. The statements are executed, one by one, in the same order as they are written. In this example, x, y, and are given values, and finally z is displayed: 
		<pre><code>
//Example: a and b are variables
var x = 2;
var y = 7;
var z = x + y;
document.getElementById("demo").innerHTML = z;            
</code></pre>                        
    </p>
    <bookmark title="w3schools JavaScript tutorial" url="http://www.w3schools.com/js/default.asp"/>        
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
		<exercise file="xc/04.01.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/04.02.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/04.03.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/04.04.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/04.05.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/04.06.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/04.07.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/04.08.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge04.png" alt="Badge 4" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>Why JavaScript is important?</li>
		<li>What kind of language is JavaScript?</li>
		<li>Where can I run JavaScript code?</li>
		<li>How to add JavaScript Code to a web page?</li>
		<li>How to run JavaScript Code on a web page?</li>
		<li>How do I write code comments?</li>
		<li>Why do I write code comments?</li>
		<li>What is a dom tree?</li>
		<li>How to attach an event listener to a button?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	
	<part title="5 Variables" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		<p><img src="img/urlsquirrel_variable.png" class="bordered"/></p>
		<p>
		Variables are containers for storing data values.
		</p>
		<slides title="Slideshow" url="slides/part5.html"/>
		<pre><code>
//Example: a and b are variables
var a = 5;
var b = 10;</code></pre>
		<p>
Variables can be used in expressions (see artihmetic operators below).		
		</p>
		<pre><code>//Example: expression
var c = a + b;</code></pre><p>All variables must be indentified with unique names. Identifiers are case-sensitive in javascript.

In javaScript '=' operator is an assignment operator, not an equal to operator.</p>
<p>In JavaScript, there are tree primitive <b>datatypes</b>: String, Number and Boolean.</p>
<p>JavaScript is loosely typed which means that you don't have to declare the type of a variable.</p>
		<pre><code>// JavaScript primitive datatypes
var length = 100; // Number (Either integer or floating point numbers
var name = "John" // String
var x = true; // Boolean: true or false </code></pre>
            
		<p><b>Arithmetic operators</b> in JavaScript.</p>
		<p><table class="table table-striped table-bordered table-condensed">
		<tr><td>+</td><td>Addition</td></tr>
		<tr><td>-</td><td>Subtraction</td></tr>
		<tr><td>*</td><td>Multiplication</td></tr>
		<tr><td>/</td><td>Division</td></tr>
		<tr><td>%</td><td>Modulus</td></tr>
		<tr><td>++</td><td>Increment</td></tr>
		<tr><td>--</td><td>Decrement</td></tr>
		</table></p>
        <p>Operator precedence describes the order in which operations are performed in an arithmetic expression. As in traditional school      mathematics, multiplication (*) and division (/) have higher precedence than addition (+) and subraction (-). And the precedence can be changed by using parentheses.
        </p>
        <p>The increment operator (++) increments numbers and the decrement operator (--) decrements numbers.</p>
		<p><pre><code>// Example
var x = 3;
x++; // Increments x by one
 </code></pre></p>            
<bookmark title="w3schools Variable" url="http://www.w3schools.com/js/js_variables.asp"/>
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
			<exercise file="xc/05.01.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/05.02.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/05.03.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/05.04.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/05.05.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/05.06.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/05.09.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/05.10.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge05.png" alt="Badge 5" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>Why and where do I need variables?</li>
		<li>What is the concept of a variable?</li>
		<li>What types of variables there are available?</li>
		<li>How to assign a value to a variable?</li>
		<li>How to read a value from a variable?</li>
		<li>How to debug the variable values?</li>
		<li>How do I show a variable value on a web page?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	
	
	<part title="6 Conditions" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		<slides title="Slideshow" url="slides/part6.html"/>
		<h3>If statement</h3>
		<p><b>If statement</b> defines a block of code which is executed if condition is true</p>
		<p><pre><code>
if (condition) {
    block of code to be executed if the condition is true
} 		
		</code></pre></p>
		<p><pre><code>
// Example		
if (hour &lt; 12) {
	say =  "Good morning";
}	
		</code></pre></p>				
		<h3>Else statement</h3>
		<p><b>Else statement</b> defines a block of code which is executed if condition is false</p>
		<p><pre><code>
if (condition) {
    block of code to be executed if the condition is true
} else { 
    block of code to be executed if the condition is false
}	
		</code></pre></p>
		<p><pre><code>
// Example		
if (score &lt; 100) {
	say = "Try again"; 
} 
else {
	say = "Well done";
}
		</code></pre></p>	
		<h3>Else if statement</h3>		
		<p><b>Else if statement</b> can be used to specify new condition if the first condition is false</p>
		<p><pre><code>
if (condition1) {
    block of code to be executed if condition1 is true
} else if (condition2) {
    block of code to be executed if the condition1 is false and condition2 is true
 } else {
    block of code to be executed if the condition1 is false and condition2 is false
}	
		</code></pre></p>
		<p><pre><code>
if (score &lt; 100) {
	say = "Try again"; 
} 
else if (score &lt; 1000){
	say = "Well done";
}
else {
	say = "Great result!";
}
		</code></pre></p>
		<h3>Operators</h3>
		<p><b>Comparison operators</b> are used to determine equality or difference between values or variables.</p>
		<p><table class="table table-striped table-bordered table-condensed">
		<tr><td>==</td><td>  equal to</td></tr>
		<tr><td>===</td><td>  equal value and equal type</td></tr>
		<tr><td>!=</td><td>  not equal</td></tr>
		<tr><td>!==</td><td>  not equal value or not equal type</td></tr>
		<tr><td>&gt;</td><td>  greater than</td></tr>
		<tr><td>&lt;</td><td>  less than</td></tr>
		<tr><td>&gt;=</td><td>  greater than or equal to</td></tr>
		<tr><td>&lt;=</td><td>  less than or equal to</td></tr>		
		</table></p>
		
		<p><b>Logical operators</b> allows you to combine multiple conditions into one expression.</p>
		<p><table class="table table-striped table-bordered table-condensed">
		<tr><td>&amp;&amp;</td><td>  and</td></tr>
		<tr><td>||</td><td>  or</td></tr>
		<tr><td>!</td><td>  not</td></tr>	
		</table></p>
		<bookmark title="Conditional Web Application" url="http://jsbin.com/jenuxa/edit?js,output"/>
		<bookmark title="w3schools Conditions" url="http://www.w3schools.com/js/js_if_else.asp"/>
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
		<exercise file="xc/06.01.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/06.02.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/06.03.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/06.05.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/06.06.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/06.07.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/06.08.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/06.09.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge06.png" alt="Badge 6" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>Why and where do I need conditions?</li>
		<li>How can I write a conditional statement (if)?</li>
		<li>How can I write an alternative path (else)?</li>
		<li>What kind of operators there are available?</li>
		<li>How to debug conditional code?</li>
		<li>How do I make conditional features on a web page?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	

	<part title="7 Functions" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		<slides title="Slideshow" url="slides/part7.html"/>
		<p>
		A JavaScript function is a block of code designed to perform a particular task. A JavaScript function is executed by invoking it (calling it).</p>
		<p><br/>Values can be passed to a function, and the function can return a value.</p>
		<p><img src="img/urlsquirrel_function.png" class="bordered"/></p>
        <p>JavaScript contains a lot of core API functions for different purposes. One example is alert function which is used to show alert messages to the user.</p>
        <p><pre><code>//Example usage of alert function
alert("This is alert message");</code></pre></p> 
            <bookmark title="Try it yourself" url="http://www.w3schools.com/js/tryit.asp?filename=tryjs_alert"/>            
		<p>Function is defined with <b>function</b> keyword followed by a function name and parentheses. The code to be executed by the function, is placed inside curly brackets {}</p>
<p><pre><code>
function name(parameter1, parameter2) {
 code to be executed
}</code></pre></p>
<p>
The function will stop when <b>return</b> statement is reached. If the function was invoked from JavaScript statement, it will return executing the code after invoking statement.
</p>
<p><pre><code>
// Function example
var a = calcSum(5, 12);  // Function call, sum is returned to variable a

function calcSum(x, y) {
  return x + y;         // Function stops and returns  
}</code></pre></p>
            <p>JavaScript <b>methods</b> are the actions that can be performed on objects. Methods are saved as a property containing a function definition. Good example of methods are Math objects methods. The Math object allows you to perform mathematical tasks.</p>
<p><pre><code>
// Math example
Math.sqrt(10);  // Returns the square root of 10 
</code></pre></p>
<p>
<b>Why functions?</b>
You can reuse code by defining the code once, and use it many times. You can use the same code many times with different arguments, to produce different results.
</p>
<bookmark title="w3schools Functions" url="http://www.w3schools.com/js/js_functions.asp"/>
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
			<exercise file="xc/07.01.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/07.02.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/07.03.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/07.04.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/07.05.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/07.06.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/07.07.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/07.09.xml"/>
			<exercise file="xc/07.10.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge07.png" alt="Badge 7" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>Why and where do I need functions?</li>
		<li>How do I define a function?</li>
		<li>How do I call a function?</li>
		<li>What is a parameter?</li>
		<li>What is a return value?</li>
		<li>How do I pass a parameter to a function?</li>
		<li>How do I use a parameter inside a function?</li>
		<li>How do I return a value from a function?</li>
		<li>How do I save a return value from a function?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	
	<part title="8 Loops" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		<slides title="Slideshow" url="slides/part8.html"/>
		<p><img src="img/urlsquirrel_loop.png" class="bordered"/></p>
		<p>There are situations when we need to execute a block of code several number of times, and is often referred to as a loop</p>
		<p>JavaScript has three main looping mechanism</p>
		<ul>
		<li>For loop</li>
		<li>While loop</li>
		<li>Do-While loop (not covered in this course)</li>		
		</ul>
		<h2>While loop</h2>
		<p>A while loop is suitable, if you don't know how many times loop should be repeated</p>
		<p>The syntax of a while loop is</p>
		<p><pre><code>while(condition)
{
   block of code to be executed
}</code></pre></p>
<p>The following while loop iterates as long as n is less than five.</p>
<p><pre><code>var n = 0;
while (n &lt; 5) {
  n++;
  //more statements
}</code></pre></p>
		<h2>For loop</h2>
		<p>The syntax of a for loop is</p>
		<p><pre><code>for(initialization; condition; update)
{
   block of code to be executed
}</code></pre></p>
<p>The following for statement starts by declaring the variable i and initializing it to 0. It checks that i is less than ten, performs the two succeeding statements, and increments i by 1 after each pass through the loop.</p>
		<p><pre><code>
// For loop example
for (var i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++) {
   console.log(i);
   // more statements
}
</code></pre></p>

		<bookmark title="Animation example" url="http://jsbin.com/ludowo/edit?js,output"/>
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
		<exercise file="xc/08.01.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/08.02.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/08.03.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/08.04.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/08.05.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/08.06.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/08.07.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/08.08.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge08.png" alt="Badge 8" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>Why and where do I need loops?</li>
		<li>How do I make an endless loop?</li>
		<li>How do I make a loop that stops?</li>
		<li>How do I make a while loop?</li>
		<li>How do I make a for loop?</li>
		<li>When should I use a for loop?</li>
		<li>When should I use a while loop?</li>
		<li>How do I make an animation on a web?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	

	<part title="9 Arrays" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		<p><b>Arrays</b> are used to store multiple values in a single variable</p>
<p><pre><code>// Array syntax
var arrayName = [item1, item2, item3,...];</code></pre></p>	
<p><pre><code>// Array example
var pets = ["Dog", "Cat", "Snake"];</code></pre></p>
<p>You refer to array elements by using the index number. Indexing of array elements starts from 0.</p>
<p><pre><code>// Referring example
var myPet = pets[0]; // myPet is Dog</code></pre></p>
<p>Arrays has property <b>length</b> which returns the number of elements in the array.</p>
<p><pre><code>// Array length property
var a = pets.length;</code></pre></p>
<h3>Looping the arrays</h3>
<p>The best way to loop through arrays are using <b>for</b>-loops and <b>length</b> property</p>
<p><pre><code>// Looping the arrays
var index;
var pets = ["Dog", "Cat", "Snake"];
for (index = 0; index &lt; pets.length; index++) {
	text = text + pets[index];
}</code></pre></p>

<bookmark title="w3schools Arrays" url="http://www.w3schools.com/js/js_arrays.asp"/>			
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
		<exercise file="xc/09.01.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/09.02.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/09.04.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/09.05.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/09.06.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/09.07.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/09.08.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge09.png" alt="Badge 9" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>Why and where do I need arrays?</li>
		<li>How do I put numbers in an array?</li>
		<li>How do I put strings in an array?</li>
		<li>How do I put objects in an array?</li>
		<li>How to loop an array with a forEach-callback?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	

	<part title="10 Objects" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="success" title="KNOWLEDGE">
            <p>Objects are variables that can contain multiple values. The following code assigns many values to variable named student.</p>
            <p><pre><code>var student = {firstname:"John", lastname:"Smith", studentnr=100232, department="IT"};</code></pre></p>    
            <p>The values are written as <b>name:value</b> pairs. The name:value pairs are called as <b>properties</b></p>
            <p>You can access object properties in two ways:</p>
<p><pre><code>objectName.propertyName</code></pre></p>
            <p>or</p>
<p><pre><code>objectName[propertyName]</code></pre></p>
<p><pre><code>//Example
student.firstname; // is John</code></pre></p>
<bookmark title="w3schools Objects" url="http://www.w3schools.com/js/js_objects.asp"/>	                     
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
		<exercise file="xc/10.01.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/10.05.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/10.06.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/10.09.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge10.png" alt="Badge 10" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>Why and where do I need Objects?</li>
		<li>How do I save structured data on a single variable?</li>
		<li>How do I create an object literal?</li>
		<li>What is an attribute?</li>
		<li>What is an attribute name?</li>
		<li>What is an attribute value?</li>
		<li>What is a method?</li>
		<li>How do I read data from an attribute?</li>
		<li>How do I change the attribute value?</li>
		<li>How do I create an object with the new-notation?</li>
		<li>How do I collect object data from a web page form?</li>
		<li>How do I print object data on a web page?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	

	<part title="11 Application Lifecycle" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
            <p>The software requirements are description of features and functionalities of the target system. Requirements gathering is an essential part of the software development process. There are multiple techinques for requirement gathering like
        <ul>
            <li>Questionnaires</li>
            <li>Interviews</li>
            <li>Observation</li>
            <li>Prototyping</li>    
        </ul>
        <br/>Software requirements specification is a documented description of the intended purpose and environment for the software.</p>
        <p><br/>Software design is a process to transform user requirements into some form, which helps the programmers in software implementation. There are different aspects in software design:
        <ul>
            <li>Architecture design: How subsystems and components will be connected and how they interact</li>
            <li>Class design: Different features of classes</li>
            <li>User interface design</li>
            <li>Algorithm design</li>    
        </ul>                
        </p>
        <p>The goals of a good design are: Increasing profit by redusing the cost, fulfilling the requirements, accelerating development and good quality.</p>
        </section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
		<exercise file="xc/11.01.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/11.02.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/11.03.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/11.04.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/11.05.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge11.png" alt="Badge 11" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>What is a software development project?</li>
		<li>How to gather software requirements?</li>
		<li>How to design an application?</li>
		<li>How to test an application?</li>
		<li>How to handle the deployment?</li>
		<li>How to handle the maintenance?</li>
		<li>Why do you need documentation?</li>
		<li>What is a revision control system?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	
	
	<part title="12 Development methods" icon="briefcase" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
            <p>There are various software development methodologies
            <ul>
            <li>Waterfall</li>
            <li>Agile</li>
            <li>RAD</li>
            <li>And so on...</li>
            </ul>
            A methodology is a model, which project managers employ for the design, planning, implementation and achievement of their project objectives. There are different project management methodologies to benefit different projects.
            </p>
            <p><br/>Waterfall is traditional method for software development project. Development moves from concept, through design, implementation, testing, installation, troubleshooting, and ends up at operation and maintenance. Each phase of development proceeds in strict order. (<a href="http://www.tutorialspoint.com/sdlc/sdlc_waterfall_model.htm">Tutorialspoint</a>)</p>
            <p><br/>
                <img src="img/waterfall.png" width="350" heigth="350"/>
            </p>
            <p><br/>Agile development is a term that was derived from the Agile Manifesto, which was written in 2001.<br/><br/>Agile manifesto: The four main principles
            <ul>
                <li>Individuals and interactions over processes and tools</li>
                <li>Working software over comprehensive documentation</li>
                <li>Customer collaboration over contract negotiation</li>
                <li>Responding to change over following a plan</li>
            </ul>
            <a href="http://www.agilemanifesto.org/">Manifesto for Agile Software Development</a>
            </p>
            <p><br/>'Agile' is an umbrella term used for identifying various models used for agile development, such as Scrum. Scrum is a management framework for incremental product development using one or more cross-functional, self-organizing teams.</p>
            <p><br/>The Scrum framework consists of Scrum Teams and their associated roles, events, artifacts, and rules. The rules of Scrum bind together the events, roles, and artifacts, governing the relationships and interaction between them. (<a href="https://www.scrumalliance.org/why-scrum/scrum-guide#sthash.pxeDKa6k.dpuf">Scrum Alliance</a>)
            </p>            
            <p><br/>Kanban is another framework based on the Agile methodology. A Kanban team is only focusing on the work that is currently in progress. There is regular fixed length sprints in the Scrum but in Kanban the work is continuous flow. There is no any fixed roles in Kanban. Some companies might work by mixing the Scrum and Kanban.<br/><br/>Kanban board is used to visualize work in team environment. Every team member can easilly get overview of their current workload.<br/><br/><img src="img/kanbanflow.png"/></p>
            <bookmark title="Learn About Scrum" url="https://www.scrumalliance.org/why-scrum"/>
            <video title="Intro to Kanban" youtubeid="R8dYLbJiTUE"/>
            <video title="What is Software Engineering" youtubeid="La_4LZQXAgo"/>
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
		<exercise file="xc/12.01.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/12.02.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/12.03.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/12.04.xml"/>
		<exercise file="xc/12.05.xml"/>
		</section>
		<section type="info" title="CHECKPOINT">
		<badgeImg><img src="img/badge12.png" alt="Badge 12" class="badgeicon"/></badgeImg>
		<ol>
		<li>What is a waterfall model?</li>
		<li>What is an agile method?</li>
		<li>What are the principles of agile software development?</li>
		<li>What is Scrum?</li>
		<li>What is Kanban?</li>
		<li>What is Lean?</li>
		</ol>
		</section>
	</part>
	
	<part title="ROUNDUP" icon="refresh" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="KNOWLEDGE">
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="SKILLS">
        		<exercise file="xc/13.01.xml"/>
        		<exercise file="xc/13.02.xml"/> 
        		<exercise file="xc/13.03.xml"/>
        		<exercise file="xc/13.04.xml"/>             
		</section>
	</part>


	<part title="EXAM" icon="time" type="default">
		<section type="info" title="INSTRUCTIONS">
			<ul>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
				<li>asdf qwerty</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section type="success" title="TAKE THE EXAM">
			<exam title="Start" url="http://www.google.com"/>
		</section>
	</part>
</course>
	
